<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The articles and conditions of the perpetuall peace concluded between the most potent King of Spaine, &amp;c. on the one partie, and the high and mightie Lords, the States Generall of the Vnited Netherlands, on the other partie, subscribed and sealed the 13th. of Ianuary, 1648. At Munster.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90643</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1985A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E434_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206224</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895821</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895821</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153480</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90643)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153480)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2367:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The articles and conditions of the perpetuall peace concluded between the most potent King of Spaine, &amp;c. on the one partie, and the high and mightie Lords, the States Generall of the Vnited Netherlands, on the other partie, subscribed and sealed the 13th. of Ianuary, 1648. At Munster.</title>
                  <author>Philip IV, King of Spain, 1605-1665. aut</author>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at Rotterdam by Haest van Voortganck, printer of the Articles of the Peace, 1648. And reprinted at London by Robert White,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: The Earl of Peneranda [and 8 others].</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 31".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Spain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spain --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153480:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153480:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ARTICLES AND CONDITIONS OF THE <hi>PERPET<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ALL PEACE,</hi> Concluded between the moſt Potent King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> &amp;c. on the one partie, and the High and Mightie Lords, the <hi>States Generall</hi> of the <hi>Vnited Netherlands,</hi> on the other partie, Subſcribed and Sealed the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> 1648.</p>
            <p>At <hi>M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NSTER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Rotterdam</hi> by <hi>Haeſt van Voortganck,</hi> Printer of the Articles of the Peace, 1648. And Reprinted at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>Robert White,</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:153480:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153480:2"/>
            <head>The Lords States Generall of the United Provinces of the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the name, and to the honour of God, Know all men, that after a tedious proſecution of bloody warres, which ſo many yeares have oppreſſed the poople, ſubjects, Kingdomes, and lands, being under the obedience of the Lord the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the Lords the States Generall of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited <hi>Netherlands;</hi> the ſaid Lords, the King, and the States, moved with all Chriſtian compaſſion, and deſire on both ſides, to make an end of the common miſeries, and to avoid the ſad proſecution, deſtruction, dammage and perills, which might follow by a further proceeding in the <hi>Low-Countrie</hi> warres, as alſo by ſpreading it to other cities and countries, and lands and ſeas lying farre off, and to change the evill effects of the ſame into an acceptable good and upright-peace, and the ſweet fruits of a full and firme reſt, to the comfort of the people and countries which are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their obedience, and the reparation of the dammages paſt; for the generall welfare, not only of the <hi>Low-countries,</hi> but alſo of all Chriſtendome, enviting and entreating other Princes and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates, that by the bleſſing of God they may be moved to the like compaſſion, and eſchewing of deſtruction, ſpoile and diſorders, which the heavie plague of warre hath ſo long and ſo heavily cauſed them to feele; for the obtaining of ſo good an end, and wiſhed eye-marke; the ſaid Lords, <hi>Don Phillippo</hi> the fourth King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the States General of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces, have deputed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, viz. the ſaid Lord King of <hi>Spaine, Don Gaſper de Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camonte,</hi> and <hi>Guſman</hi> Earle of <hi>Penaranda,</hi> Lord of <hi>Aldea, Seca,</hi> and <hi>Forteran,</hi> Knight of the Order of <hi>Alcantare</hi> perpetuall Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrator of the Command of <hi>Dayniel,</hi> of the Order of <hi>Calatraia,</hi> Gentleman of the Chamber of his Majeſtie, and of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and Chamber, Extraordinary Ambaſſador for his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Majeſtie, and the chiefe Plenipotentarie for the Treatie of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Peace the honourable <hi>Anthony Bruyn,</hi> Knight, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellour of his Catholick Majeſtie in his Councell of State, and high
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153480:3"/>Councell for the afaires of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> in <hi>Burgundy</hi> about his perſon, and his Plenipotentiarie for the Treaties of peace of the generall Peace: And the Lords the States generall of the <hi>United Provinces;</hi> the right Honorable <hi>Bartholt van Gendt,</hi> Lord of <hi>Loenen</hi> and <hi>Meinerſwiick, Amptman</hi> and <hi>Dyckgrave</hi> of <hi>Bommel, Tielre,</hi> and <hi>Bommeler-weerde,</hi> deputed for the States Generall by the Province of <hi>Gelderland,</hi> the Right Honorable <hi>John van Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> Lord of <hi>Mateneſſe, Riviere Opmeer, Souteveen,</hi> deputed for the Aſſembly of the States Generall by the order of the Knighthood and Gentrie of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſtfrieſland,</hi> High Privicouncellor of <hi>Schieland;</hi> the Honorable <hi>Adrian Pauw,</hi> Knight, Lord of <hi>Hamſted, Hoogerſmilde, &amp;c.</hi> chief Preſiding Counſellor and Treaſurer of the Earledome of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſtfrieſland,</hi> and deputed on the behalfe of the ſame Province for the Aſſembly of the Lords States Generall; the Honorable <hi>John de Knuyt,</hi> Knight, Lord of Old and New <hi>Voſmer,</hi> chief repreſenting the Gentrie in the States, and the Councell of the Earldome of <hi>Zealand,</hi> and the Admiraltie the chief Counſellor of his Highneſſe the Lord Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> Ordinarie Deputie in the Aſſembly of the Lords the States Gen the Honorable <hi>Godert van Reede,</hi> Lord of <hi>Nederhorſt, Vredeland,</hi> ſhort <hi>Houff, Orermeer, Horſt, Waert, &amp;c.</hi> Preſident of the Honorable Gentrie &amp; Knighthood of the land of <hi>Vtretcht,</hi> and in the name thereof appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at the Aſſembly of the Lords the States Generall; the Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Francis van Donia,</hi> Lord of <hi>Humena</hi> and <hi>Hielſum, &amp;c.</hi> Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the Aſſembly of the Lords the States Generall, on the behalf of the Province of <hi>Frieſland;</hi> the Honorable <hi>William Ripperda,</hi> Lord of <hi>Hengeloo Bolbergen, Cabulo,</hi> and <hi>Ruſſenburg, &amp;c.</hi> Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the States General for the Knighthood &amp; Gentrie of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Over-Yſſel,</hi> the Honorable <hi>Adrian Clant</hi> at <hi>Stedum,</hi> Lord of <hi>Mutterſum, &amp;c.</hi> Ordinarie Deputie in the aſſembly of the States Generall on the behalf of the Province of the Citie of <hi>Groeningen</hi> and lands adjacent, all extraordinarie Ambaſſadors in <hi>Germanie,</hi> and Plenipotentiaries of the ſaid Lords the States Generall for the Treatie of the generall peace, all of them furniſhed with full power or procurations, inſerted at the foote hereof; who being aſſembled together in the Citie of <hi>Munſter</hi> in <hi>Weſtphalia</hi> with common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent — for the Treatie of the common reſt in Chriſtendome, by vertue of their ſaid Letters of Atturney and in the names of the ſaid Lords the King and States, have made, concluded, and agreed on the Articles following.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:153480:3"/>
            <head>Articles of the <hi>Peace</hi> concluded at MUNSTER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Mprimis.</hi> The ſaid Lord the King doth declare and acknowledge, that the ſaid Lords the States generall of the United <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and the ſeverall Provinces of the ſame, with all their aſſociated countries, cities, and lands belonging to them, are free and ſoveraign Cities, Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and lands, of and againſt whom, nor their aſſociated coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, cityes, and lands, the ſaid Lord the King doth not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend any thing, nor now, nor hereafter, for himſelfe, his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, and poſterity, ſhall pretend any thing, and in ſequell hereunto is content to treat with the ſame Lords States, as he doth by theſe preſents, for a <hi>perpetuall Peace,</hi> on the conditions here under-written and declared: to wit:</p>
            <p>
               <label>2.</label> That the ſaid Peace ſhall be good, firm, faithfull, and infran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, and that in order hereunto, there ſhall be a ceſſation of all Acts of hoſtility whatſoever, between the ſaid Lord the King, and the States generall, as well at ſea, and other waters, as at land, in all their reſpective Kingdoms, Countries, Lands, and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for all their ſubjects and Inhabitants, of any qualitie or condition whatſoever they be, without exception of places or perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <label>3.</label> Each one ſhall keep, and preſently occupy the countryes, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, places, lands, and dominions, which they do at preſent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, without therein to be troubled or hindred directly nor indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, in what manner ſoever it be, wherein is underſtood to comprehend the villages, towns, high-lands, &amp; low-lands depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereon: and in the ſequell thereof, the whole Maioralty of <hi>Buſſe,</hi> as alſo the Lordſhips, cities, caſtles, villages, townes,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153480:4"/>high lands, and low-lands depending on the ſaid Maioralty of the <hi>Buſſe,</hi> the City and Marquiſate of <hi>Bergen op Zoam:</hi> the City and Barony of <hi>Breda:</hi> the City of <hi>Maeſtricht,</hi> and the confines thereof: as alſo the Earldome of <hi>Proonehoffe:</hi> the Earle and land of <hi>Cuyck, Hulſt,</hi> and <hi>Bayliwick</hi> of <hi>Hulſt,</hi> and <hi>Hulſter-Ambacht;</hi> and as alſo <hi>Axele-Ambacht,</hi> lying on the ſouth and north of <hi>Geule,</hi> as alſo the Forts, which the ſaid Lords States have in the Land of <hi>Waes,</hi> and all the other cities and places which the ſaid Lords the States hold in <hi>Brabant, Flanuders,</hi> and elſewhere, remain to the ſaid Lords States, in all the rights, ſoveraignities, and ſuperiorities of the ſame, nothing excepted, and every of them, as they do hold the Provinces of the United Provinces: Provided that all the reſt of the Land of <hi>Waes,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the ſaid Forts, ſhall remain to the King of <hi>Spaine:</hi> for what concerns the free Quarters of <hi>Over-maſe:</hi> to wit, <hi>Valcken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge, Dalen,</hi> and <hi>S'Hertogenrade:</hi> they ſhall remain in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition wherein they at preſent are: and in caſe of diſpute, and controverſy, the ſame ſhall be ſent to the <hi>Bipartite Chamber,</hi> of which is hereafter ſpoken.</p>
            <p>
               <label>4</label> The ſubjects or inhabitants of the ſaid Lord the King and the States, ſhall have all good correſpondence and friendſhip toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without remembring the offences or damages, which they have formerly ſuffered: they ſhall alſo come and abide in the countries, the one of the other, and there uſe their trade and commerce in all ſecurity, as well at ſea, other waters, as at land.</p>
            <p>
               <label>5.</label> The navigations and commerce for the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> ſhall be maintained, according and in conformity to the Grants therefore already given or yet to be given; and for aſſurance thereof, this preſent treaty (and the ratification on both ſides to be performed,) ſhall reach: and under the ſaid treaty ſhall be comprehended all Potentates, Nations and People, with whom their Lordſhips, or thoſe of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> or <hi>Weſt-Indy</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny on their behalf, within the bounds of their Patent are in friendſhip and allyance: and each one, to wit, the ſaid Lord the King and the Lords and States reſpectively ſhall hold and enjoy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153480:4"/>ſuch dominions, cities, caſtles, ſtrengths, trade, and landes, in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> as alſo in <hi>Brazill,</hi> as alſo on the coaſts of <hi>Aſia, Africa,</hi> and <hi>America</hi> ſeverally, as the ſame Lords the King and the States reſpectively have and hold; among which are ſpecially contained the places ſince the year 1641. taken from the Lords Sates, and occupied by the Portingalls, or which they hereafter without the breach of this preſent Treaty may get and hold: And the governours as well of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt-India</hi> company of the United Provinces, as alſo the Miniſters, high and low officers, ſouldiers, and mariners, being, or which have been in actuall ſervice, as alſo thoſe which continue out of the ſame ſervices reſpectively, as well here in this Country as in the limits of the ſaid Company, and may hereafter be imployed, be free &amp; untroubled in all the lands which are under the obedience of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> they may travell, trade, and go as all other inhabitants of this State. Further it is beſpoke and ſtipulated, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſhall remain in their voyages in the ſame manner as they yet hold the ſame in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> without extending themſelves further: as likewiſe the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the United <hi>Netherlands</hi> ſhall forbear to frequent or occupy the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> places in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>6.</label> And what concerns the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> the Subjects and Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Kingdoms, Provinces, and lands of the ſaid Lords, the King, and States reſpectively, ſhall forbear to ſayle and trade in all the havens and places, with the lodges, caſtles, and all other places, held and poſſeſſed by one or the other party, to wit, the Subjects of the ſaid Lord the King ſhall not ſayle unto, and trade in the havens and places which are held by the ſaid Lords States, nor alſo the Subjects of the ſaid Lords States in thoſe places which are kept by the ſaid Lord the King; and under the places which the ſaid Lords States do poſſeſſe, ſhall be alſo comprehended the places which the Portingals ſince the year 1641. have taken from the ſaid Lords States, in <hi>Brazill,</hi> as alſo all other places which they at preſent hold, ſo long as they ſhall be under the <hi>Portingals;</hi> without that the aforegoing Articles may derogate the contents of this Article.</p>
            <p>
               <label>7.</label> And ſince a good long time is needfull to advertiſe thoſe that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153480:5"/>are out of the ſaid limits with power and ſhips to deſiſt from all acts of Hoſtility, it is agreed that the peace, for the bounds of the Patent formerly granted or yet by continuance to be granted to the <hi>Eaſt-Indie</hi> Company of the United <hi>Netherlands,</hi> ſhall not begin till a year after the date of the concluſion of the preſent peace: And what concernes the bounds of the Patent formerly by the Lords States generall agreed, or yet by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance to be agreed to the <hi>Weſt-Indie</hi> Company, that the peace there ſhall not begin till a halfe year after date as above. Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that in caſe adviſe of the ſaid peace ſhall ſooner become publick on both ſides within the ſaid ſeverall Limits, that then hoſtility ſhall there ceaſe: but in caſe after the ſaid time of one year, and halfe a year, reſpectively, any Acts of Hoſtility ſhall be done within the ſaid Limits of the ſaid Patents, the damage ſhall be reſtored without delay.</p>
            <p>
               <label>8.</label> The Subjects and Inhabitants of the ſaid Countries of the ſaid Lords, the King, and the States trading in theſe Countries, the one not be bound to pay to the other more duties and impoſts then the own Subjects themſelves, ſo that the Inhabitants and Subjects of the United Provinces, ſhall be and remain exempt from the twenty <hi>per cent,</hi> or any leſſe, or any other Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt which the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> during the twelve years of truce leavied, or which he hereafter directly or indirectly would leavy on the ſaid Inhabitants and Subjects of the United Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or to charge them with more or above his own Subjects.</p>
            <p>
               <label>9.</label> The ſaid Lords, the King, and States, may not receive any du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of importation or exportation or any other, without their ſeverall Limits, on goods paſſing either by water or land.</p>
            <p>
               <label>10.</label> The Subjects of the ſaid King and States, ſhall reciprocally enjoy the ancient freedome of cuſtomes, in the lands the one of the other, of which they had peaceable poſſeſſion before the beginning of the Warres.</p>
            <p>
               <label>11.</label> The commerce, paſſage, and trade, between the reſpective Subjects, may not be hindred, and in caſe any hindrance may happen, the ſame ſhall ſeaſonably and actually be removed.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:153480:5"/>
            <p>
               <label>12.</label> And from the day of the concluſion, and ratification thereof, the King ſhall forbeare the leavying of all Tolls on the <hi>Rhyne</hi> and the <hi>Maſe</hi> which were before the warres, under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and Limits of the Vnited <hi>Netherlands,</hi> eſpecially alſo the <hi>Zealand</hi> Toll, ſo that this Toll ſhall not be given to his Majeſty in the City of <hi>Antwerp</hi> or elſewhere: Provided and on condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that from the ſaid day forwards, the States of <hi>Zealand</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocally at their charge ſhall take and pay firſt and foremoſt from the ſame day forwards, the annuall rents, which before the year 1572. were confirmed on the ſaid Tolls, and of which the owners and rent-farmers had the enjoyment and receipt, before the beginning of the ſaid warre; the which alſo the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the ſaid Tolls ſhall likewiſe do.</p>
            <p>
               <label>13.</label> White boyled ſalt coming out of the Vnited Provinces into the Countryes of his ſaid Majeſty, ſhall be there received and admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, without to be taxed higher then as bay ſalt is, and alſo that ſalt coming out of the lands of his ſaid Majeſty into the Vnited Provinces, ſhall be admitted and vented, without that the ſame be higher taxed then the ſalt of the ſaid Lords the States.</p>
            <p>
               <label>14.</label> The river the <hi>Scheld,</hi> as alſo the Channels, and the <hi>Sas, Swyn,</hi> and other ſea gaps belonging to them, ſhall remain blockt up on the ſide of the Lords States.</p>
            <p>
               <label>15.</label> The ſhips and goods coming in and out of the havens of <hi>Flanders</hi> reſpectively, ſhall be and remain taxed by the ſaid Lord the King, with ſuch Impoſts and other charges, as the goods of the <hi>Scheld,</hi> and other channels contained in the article above, are taxed or rated in coming and going reſpectively; and ſhall be hereafter agreed between the partyes on both ſides at the foot of the ſaid equall taxations.</p>
            <p>
               <label>16.</label> The Hans-cities, with all the Burgers, Inhabitants, and territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the ſame, ſhall in matter of navigation and commerce in <hi>Spain,</hi> the Realmes and Countries of <hi>Spain,</hi> enioy all and the ſame rights, freedomes, Immunities, and priviledges, which by this preſent Treaty are agreed, or hereafter may be agreed, for and on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153480:6"/>the behalfe of the Subjects and Inhabitants of the United <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands;</hi> they ſhall enjoy all the ſame rights, freedoms, immunities, priviledges, and capitulations, as well for making of Conſuls in the ports or ſea towns of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and elſewhere, where it ſhall be needfull, as for the Merchants, Factors, Ship-maſters, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners, or otherwiſe, even as the ſaid Hans towns in generall or particular have formerly had and practiſed, or ſhall hereafter get and practiſe, for the ſecurity, profit, and advantage of the navigation and commerce of their Cityes, Merchants, Factors, Aſſignes, and others, which depend on them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>17.</label> Alſo the Subjects and Inhabitants of the Countryes of the ſaid Lords the States, ſhall have the ſame ſecurity and freedome in the lands of the ſaid Lord the King, as is granted to the Subjects of the King of great Brittaine by the laſt Treaty of Peace, and ſecret Articles made with the Conſtable of <hi>Caſtile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>18.</label> The ſaid Lord the King ſhall with the firſt good opportunity grant that civill places be ordained for the burying of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes of ſuch of the ſaid Lords States party as ſhall happen to dye under the obedience of the ſaid Lord the King.</p>
            <p>
               <label>19</label> The Subjects and Inhabitants of the Countries of the ſaid Lord the King, coming into the Countries of the ſaid Lords the States, ſhall carry themſelves with all civility in matters of the publique worſhip of religion, without giving any ſcandall by words or actions, and without any reviling ſpeeches, and the ſame ſhall be obſerved by the Subjects and Inhabitants of the lands of the ſaid Lords States, coming into the lands of his Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <label>20.</label> Likewiſe the Merchants, Ship-maſters, Pilots, Maryners, their ſhips, merchandiſe, ware, and other goods belonging to them, may not be ſtopped nor areſted, by vertue of any command, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall or particular, and for whatſoever cauſe it be, either for warre, or otherwiſe, yea not under pretence to have them ſerve for the conſervation and defence of the Country: by which is not meant to containe, the ſtops and arreſts of Juſtice, in the ordinary way, by reaſon of any debts, bonds, and obliging contracts, of thoſe againſt whom the ſaid ſtoppings ſhall be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153480:6"/>made, but therein ſhall be proceeded, as is uſuall according to law and reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <label>21.</label> On both ſides ſhall be appointed ſome Juſtices in number e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, by way of a <hi>Bipartite Chamber,</hi> who ſhall reſide in the Low-countryes, and at ſuch a place as is fit, and that by turnes, ſometimes under the obedience of the one, ſometimes of the other, as it ſhall be thought good by joynt conſent; the which Judges appointed on both ſides, according to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and inſtructions which ſhall be given them, and upon which they ſhall make oath according to a certaine forme, to be for that purpoſe framed by both partyes, ſhall overlooke the dealings of the Inhabitants of the ſaid Low-countryes, and the cuſtomes and impoſts which ſhall be leavied on goods by one ſide and the other; And in caſe the ſaid Judges chance to finde that exceſſe be uſed, by either one, or the other, or on both ſides, the ſaid Judges ſhall examine the controverſy on the not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the ſaid Treaty, as alſo the contraventions thereof, which may chance to ariſe in any time and place, as well in the Countries here, as in the Kingdomes, Countries, Provinces and Iſlands lying far off in <hi>Europe,</hi> and thereof ſummarily and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſpoſe, and declare what they ſhall judge fit in conformity to the Treaty: and the ſentences and diſpoſitions of the ſaid Judges ſhall be put in execution by the ordinary Juſtice at the place where the breach hapned, or elſe againſt the perſons of the contraventors, as the occaſion ſhall require, and the ſaid or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Juſtice or Court may not remain in default of doing the ſaid execution, or ſuffer it to be done, and to repaire the ſaid breach within the time of ſix monthes, after the ſaid ordinary Court ſhall be thereunto required.</p>
            <p>
               <label>22.</label> In caſe any ſentences and Judgements be denounced between perſons of both parties, being not grounded, either in matters civill or criminall, they ſhall not be put in execution againſt the perſons of the condemned, nor their goods; And no letters of Mart or repriſall ſhall be granted, but upon knowledge of the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, and in ſuch matters for which it is permitted by the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall lawes, and conſtitutions, and according unto the order thereby made.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:153480:7"/>
               <label>23.</label> They ſhall not arrive, come in, or remain in the Havens, Bayes, Ports or roads of the countries, the one of the other, with ſhips, and men of war in any number, that might cauſe ſuſpition, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leave and permiſſion of thoſe under whom the ſaid Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, Bayes, Ports, and roads are, except they are forced by tempeſt, and forced to do the ſame through need, and to avoid any perills of the ſea.</p>
            <p>
               <label>24.</label> Thoſe whoſe goods are ſeazed and confiſcated by reaſon of the warre, or their heires, or thoſe who have their right, ſhall uſe the ſame goods, and ſhall take the poſſeſſion of them by their own authority, and by virtue of this Treaty, without that it be needfull to have recourſe to Juſtice, notwithſtanding all incorporations of the Fiſcall, morgages, gifts made, treatyes, agreements, and tranſactions, and whatſoever renuntiations may be inſerted in the ſaid tranſactions, for to exclude from a part of the goods, and thoſe whom the ſame right ſhould come to; And all goods and rights, which in ſequell of this preſent Treaty are reſtored, or are yet to be reſtored reciprocally to the old proprietors, their heires, or thoſe that have their right, ſhall be ſold by the ſaid proprietors, without that it be needfull to obtain particular conſent therefore, and in order hereunto the propriety of the rents, which have been conſtituted on the behalfe of the Fiſcall, in ſtead of the goods ſold, as alſo the rents or actions, which are laid upon the Fiſcall reſpectively, may alſo be diſpoſed of by the proprietors of them, by ſale, or otherwiſe, as their own goods.</p>
            <p>
               <label>25.</label> The which ſhall take place for the uſe of the heyres of the Lord Prince <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> yea for the rights which they have in the <hi>Salines</hi> of the County of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> which ſhall be reſtored and left to them, with the Woods which depend there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, in regard of that which ſhall not be found to be bought and paid for by his ſaid Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <label>26.</label> In which is alſo meant to be comprehended the other goods and rights, lying in the Countries of <hi>Burgundy</hi> and <hi>Charlois,</hi> and what in order to the Treaty of the ninteenth of <hi>Aprill</hi> 1609. and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153480:7"/>the ſeventh of <hi>January</hi> 1610. reſpectively, is not yet reſtored, to the ſaid proprietors and their heires, or thoſe who have their rights on both ſides, ſhall every where with the firſt be reſtored in good faith.</p>
            <p>
               <label>27.</label> As alſo therein is meant to be comprehended the goods and rights, which after the expiration of the League of 12 yeares, by ſentence of the high Councell of <hi>Mechleu,</hi> to the prejudice of the Fiſcall were adjudged to late Earle <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> or in what manner the ſaid Earle had the poſſeſſion of them, in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever places, lands, or dominions, the ſaid adjudged goods and rights may lye, and by whomſoever they may be poſſeſſed: the which ſentence, by virtue of this Treaty, is, and is held as void, and all other poſſeſſion gotten as aforeſaid, is made void.</p>
            <p>
               <label>28.</label> And what concerns the ſuit of <hi>Caſtelbelijn,</hi> commenced in the life of the ſaid late Lord Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> before the high Councell of <hi>Mecheleu</hi> againſt the Atturny generall of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> foraſmuch as the ſaid ſuit was not ended within the tearm of a year, after the proſecution made therein, as in the fourteenth Article of the League for twelve years was promiſed to be done, it is agreed that preſently after the concluding and ratification of this preſent Treaty, the Fiſcals in the name of his Majeſty, or in whoſe name ſoever the ſame may be, ſhall preſently make aſſignement of all the goods claimed in the ſaid ſuit, and by whomſoever and by what right ſoever the ſame are poſſeſſed, alſo in the name, and on the behalfe as afore, ſhall renounce all actions and pretences wich the ſaid Fiſcall may any wiſe have, or could pretend on the ſaid goods, for preſently after the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and ratification of this Treaty, and by virtue thereof, and without any recourſe in Law, to be received by the preſent Lord Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> his heires and ſucceſſours, or thoſe having his right, and taken into free and unincumbred poſſeſſion, but the profits received and enjoyed, with the charges of them, unto the day of the concluding of this Treaty, ſhall remain to the uſe of the Fiſcall.</p>
            <p>
               <label>29.</label> In caſe difficulty be in any place found, in the reſtitution of the goods and rights which muſt be reſtored, the Judge of that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153480:8"/>place ſhall without delay cauſe the reſtitution to be effected, and take the ſhorteſt way therein, without that the reſtitution may be delayed under pretence of the non-payment of the principall or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>30.</label> The Subjects and Inhabitants of the United <hi>Netherlands,</hi> may where ever they are in the Countries under the obedience of the ſaid Lord the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> be aſſiſted with ſuch Advocates, Atturnyes, Notaryes, Sollicitors, and Executors, as they ſhall think good, whereunto they ſhall be alſo choſen by the ordinary Judges, when it ſhall be needfull, and the ſaid Judges ſhall be thereunto required: and reciprocally the Inhabitants and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the ſaid Lord the King, coming into the Countries of the ſaid Lords States, ſhall alſo enjoy the ſame aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <label>31.</label> In caſe the Fiſcall hath cauſed any confiſcated goods of the one or the otherſide to be ſold, of thoſe to whom the ſame muſt belong by virtue of this Treaty they ſhall be bound to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with the Intereſt of the price, at the rate of the ſixteenth penny thereof, to be annually paid by the proximity of thoſe who poſſeſſe the ſaid goods, elſe it ſhall be permitted to them to addreſſe themſelvs to the Lands of the Inheritances ſold, with this proviſo, that in ſtead of the goods ſold, the rents or intereſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, or the principall thereof, by &amp; in the name of the reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Fiſcals letters patents, ſhall be granted to the uſe of the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, their heires, or ſuch as have their action, which ſhal ſerve them for a declaratory evidence, in conformity to the Treaty, with an aſſignement of the annuall payment on ſome Rent-maſter in the Province, where they are ſold or remitted: the which Rent-maſter ſhall be named therein, and the price ſhall be accounted according to the firſt ſale, being done publickly, or otherwiſe as is fitting, the firſt year of which rent ſhall be ended a year after the date of the concluſion and ratification of this preſent Treaty.</p>
            <p>
               <label>32.</label> But in caſe the ſaid ſales were done by juſtice, for due and lawfull debts of thoſe to whom the ſaid goods uſed to belong before the confiſcations, it ſhall be permitted them, or their heyres, and thoſe that have their right, to take them to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, paying the price within a year to be accounted from the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153480:8"/>day of this preſent Treaty, after which time they ſhall not be any more receiveable for it, and the ſaid allowance and ſale be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by them done, they may diſpoſe thereof as they ſhall ſee good, without that it be needfull to obtaine any other leave for it.</p>
            <p>
               <label>33.</label> Yet it is provided, that the ſaid retaking ſhall not have place for houſes ſold, which lye in Cities, which for that cauſe have been ſold the dearer, becauſe of the great inconveniency and notable dammage, which the purchaſers would have, by reaſon of the change, and repairing, which may have been done in the ſaid houſes, for which the Liquidations would be too tedious and heavie.</p>
            <p>
               <label>34.</label> And for the reparations and amendments done to other goods ſold, of which the ſale is permitted, in caſe they be claimed, the ordinary Judges ſhall doe right upon knowledge of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; the Lands and inheritances remaining morgaged for the ſumme whereunto the amendments ſhall be liquidated, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out nevertheleſſe giving leave to the ſaid purchaſers to uſe the right of Arentment, for to be paid and ſatisfied therefore.</p>
            <p>
               <label>35.</label> All undiſcovered goods and rights, moveables, and immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veables, rents, actions, debts, credits, and other things, which have not been ſeazed by the Fiſcall, upon due knowledge of the buſineſſe, before the day of the concluding, and ratification of this Treaty, ſhall remaine to the free and full diſpoſall of the owners, their heires, or ſuch as have their right, with all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, rents, revenewes, and benefits; and thoſe who have concealed the ſaid goods and rights, or their heires, ſhall not be troubled for the ſame by the reſpective Fiſcalls, but the owners, their heires, or ſuch as have their right, may have an action for the ſame againſt every one, as for their own goods.</p>
            <p>
               <label>36.</label> The trees cut down, after the finiſhing of this Treaty, and which at that day are yet ſtanding on the ground, as alſo the trees ſold, which are not yet cut downe by the ſaid day, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine to the owners, notwithſtanding any ſale made, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being bound to pay any price.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:153480:9"/>
            <p>
               <label>37.</label> The Intereſts, hvre, Farmes, and revenewes of the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Countries, Tithes, Fiſhponds, houſes, rents, and other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venewes of goods, which according to the Treaty muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, due from the day of the concluſion of this reaty, ſhall come to the proprietors, their heyres, or ſuch as have their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the whole year.</p>
            <p>
               <label>38.</label> The hyre which hath been made of confiſcated or ſeazed goods (although the ſame be made for many yeares) ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire with the yeare from the concluſion of this Treaty, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the uſe of the ſeverall places where the ſaid goods are ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate, and the hyre ſhall end from the day of the end of the Treaty, and ſhall be made good and paid to the owners, provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that in caſe the occupier of the goods hath been at any charge before the ſpring of that year, that the ſame charges ſhall be payd by the owners and occupiers, according to cuſtome, or the diſcretion of the Judge of the places where the ſame goods are ſituate.</p>
            <p>
               <label>39.</label> All ſale of confiſcated or ſeazed goods, done ſince the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the Treaty, ſhall be held null and void; as alſo the ſales made before ſuch concluſion, which were made againſt the Covenants, or agreements with any Cities in particular.</p>
            <p>
               <label>40.</label> The houſes of particular perſons, which are reſtored, or are to be reſtored according to the Treaty, ſhall not reciprocally be charged with Garriſons or otherwiſe, any higher or lower then the houſes of other Inhabitants of the like conveniency.</p>
            <p>
               <label>41.</label> None, on the one ſide nor the other, directly, nor indirectly ſhall be hindred in changing of their dwelling place, paying the duties which are impoſed there, and in caſe any hinderances hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen after the Treaty, they ſhall be preſently removed.</p>
            <p>
               <label>42.</label> In caſe any Fortifications or workes, on the one or the other ſide, with leave, and by the Authority of the Governours, be made in ſuch places as by this preſent Treaty ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, the owners of them ſhall be bound to content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153480:9"/>with the value which ſhall be made thereof by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Judges, aſwell of the ſaid places, as of the Juriſdiction they are under, except the parties agree amongſt themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, as alſo ſatisfaction ſhall be given to the owners of the goods which have been uſed for Fortifications, publike works, or Hoſpitals.</p>
            <p>
               <label>43.</label> Concerning the goods of Churches, Colleges, or other pious places, lying in the United Provinces, which were Members depending on Churches, Benefices, and Colleges, under the obedience of the ſaid Lord the King; whatſoever hath not been ſold before the cloſure of this preſent Treaty, ſhall be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven againe and reſtored to them; and they ſhall come into the poſſeſſion of them, by their own Authority and without help of Law, for to uſe the ſame, and without diſpoſing of the ſame as is here aforeſaid: But for ſuch as ſhall have been ſold before the ſaid time, or have been given in payment by the States of any of the Provinces, they ſhall be paid the annuall rent of the price, at the rate of the ſixteenth penny, by that Province which hath made the ſaid ſale, or hath given the ſaid goods in payment; and ſhall alſo have ſuch aſſignement, as they may be aſſured thereof; and the like ſhall be done and obſerved on the ſide of the ſaid Lord the King.</p>
            <p>
               <label>44.</label> For ſuch pretences and Intereſts, which the Lord Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> may have, touching ſome parcels which he doth not poſſeſſe, the ſame ſhall be accorded by a particular Treaty, to the ſatisfaction of the ſaid Lord Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> but what concernes the goods and effects which the ſaid Prince is in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of, by the grant and conceſſion of the ſaid Lords the States Generall, in the Bayliffwick of the <hi>Hulſter Ambacht,</hi> and elſewhere, of the which the ſaid Lords States a while ſince have made him a confirmation; all the ſame parcells ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in full property to the ſaid Lord Prince, and his ſucceſſors, or who have his right, without that any thing can be pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſaid goods, by vertue of any Articles of this preſent Treaty.</p>
            <p>
               <label>45.</label> Thoſe to whom the confiſcated goods muſt be reſtored, ſhall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153480:10"/>not be bound to pay the arrerages of rents, and charges annual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken, and aſſigned on the ſaid goods, for the time that they have been uſed, and if they be proſecuted and troubled for the ſame, by the one ſide or the other, they ſhall be ſent back and diſcharged; and where it is found known, that all goods of any one of the one ſide or the other ſide have been confiſcated, or ſeazed, ſo that he hath kept no meanes wherewith he could pay the rents and Intereſts of his debts, which are fallen due during the confication or ſeazure, they ſhall be acquitted not only from the charges and rents, according to the Treaty, but alſo from generall and perſonall impoſitions of the rents and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts fallen due in the ſaid time.</p>
            <p>
               <label>46.</label> Concerning ſome other points, which beſides the contents of the afore going 44.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Article, are eſpecially treated and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon, and ſubſcribed in two ſeverall writings, one of the 8.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> the other of the 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> 1647. for, and in the name of the ſaid Lord Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> the ſaid wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and all the contents of the ſame ſhall have their effect, and be confirmed, performed, and executed according to their forme and tenour, more or leſſe, as if all the ſaid points in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, or each of them in particular were word for word in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted in this preſent Treaty, notwithſtanding any clauſes of this preſent Treaty to the contrary hereof, the which clauſes it is underſtood to be derogate, and are expreſly deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by this preſent Article, and which clauſe in reſpect of the ſaid two writings, are, and ſhall be held as not made, and without that by reaſon thereof the performance and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſaid two writings, of the 8.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> and of the 27.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> 1647. may be hindred, or in any manner withheld.</p>
            <p>
               <label>47.</label> Alſo nothing may be pretended for the goods which are ſold, or agreed for to be dycked, or redycked, other then for the upſtalling or reparations for which the poſſeſſors have bound themſelves by the Treaties made thereof; with the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of the moneys furniſhed, if any have been given, alſo after the rate of the 16.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> penny as above.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:153480:10"/>
            <p>
               <label>48.</label> Sentences given for goods and rights confiſcated, with parties which have knowne the Judges, and have been legally defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhall hold, and the condemned perſons ſhall not be receiv'd to gaineſay them, but by ordinary wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>49.</label> The ſaid Lord the King doth acquit, and renounce all pretences of Redemption, and all other Lawes and pretences which he can have, or pretend in any manner, againſt the Citie of the <hi>Grave,</hi> the Land of <hi>Cuyck,</hi> it's apertenances, and the dependencies of the Barony of <hi>Brabant,</hi> formerly held in morgage by the late Lord Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> the redemption of the which morgage is diſcharged and converted into property, and delivered over to the uſe of the late Lord Prince <hi>Maurice,</hi> in <hi>December,</hi> 1611. by the Lords States generall of the united <hi>Netherlands,</hi> as So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignes of the ſaid City of <hi>Grave,</hi> and land of <hi>Cuyck,</hi> in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quell and conformable to the Letters Patents granted thereof, and by vertue of which Converſion and aſſignement, the ſaid Lord Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> that now is, his heires and ſucceſſors, or ſuch as have his right, ſhall alwayes uſe the full and whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of the ſaid City, and land of <hi>Cuyck,</hi> with all its aperte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and dependencies.</p>
            <p>
               <label>50.</label> The ſaid Lord the King doth alſo acquit and renounce, all and every the rights and pretences, either of propriety, Aſſigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or otherwiſe, which he may in any manner pretend to the City, County, or Dominion of <hi>Lingen,</hi> and foure <hi>Karts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpelen,</hi> and other rights belonging thereunto, as alſo to the Cities and Dominions of <hi>Bevergard</hi> and <hi>Kloppenburg,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pretences, on and againſt whomſoever they may be, for really and actually for ever to remaine to the ſaid Lord Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> his heires and ſucceſſors, or thoſe that have his right, in full right of propriety, according to the Letters or deed of gift and grant of the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the 5.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> dated the 3.<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of <hi>November,</hi> 1546. and the agreement made afterwards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Earle of <hi>Bueren,</hi> and the Earle of <hi>Teeckelenburg,</hi> dated the 15.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1548. and finally, according to the aſſignement made thereof in <hi>November,</hi> 1578. which the ſaid Lord the King, for what concerneth him hath confirmed,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153480:11"/>and doth confirme by the aforeſaid Treaty.</p>
            <p>
               <label>51.</label> The ſaid Lord the King, and Lords States, ſhall appoint (each in their own) the Offices of the Magiſtrates for the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Juſtice and Policies, in the Cities and ſtrong holds, which by this preſent Treaty are to be reſtored to the owners for to uſe them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>52.</label> The farrther quarter of <hi>Gelderland</hi> ſhall be exchanged for it's equivalent, and in caſe they cannot pleaſe one another about the ſaid equivalent, the ſame ſhall be put to the Biparty Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to be decided within 6. moneths after the concluſion and ratification of the Treaty.</p>
            <p>
               <label>53.</label> The ſaid Lord the King, doth bind himſelfe effectually to perfect the continuance and obſervance of all Neutrality, friendſhip, and good neighbourhood, on the behalfe of his Imperiall Majeſty and the Empire with the ſaid Lords States, unto which continuance and obſervance, the ſaid Lords States doe alſo reciprocally bind themſelves, and the Confirmation of his Emperiall Majeſty ſhall be had thereupon, within the time of two moneths; and on the behalfe of the Empire with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a year after the concluſion and ratification of the preſent Treaty.</p>
            <p>
               <label>54.</label> The moveables which are confiſcated, and the profits which are fallen due before the concluſion of the preſent Treaty, ſhall be ſubject to no reſtitution.</p>
            <p>
               <label>55.</label> The moveable actions, which ſhall be remitted by the ſaid Lord the King, or the States, to the uſe of the particular debt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, before the concluſion of this preſent Treaty, ſhall remaine cancelled on the one and the other ſide.</p>
            <p>
               <label>56.</label> The time which hath run from the beginning of the warre, ſince the yeare 1567. till the beginning of the truce of twelve yeares, as alſo, the time which hath run ſince the expiration of the ſaid truce, till the concluſion of this Treaty, ſhall not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, for to wrong, or otherwiſe to prejudice any one thereby.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:153480:11"/>
            <p>
               <label>57.</label> Thoſe who during the warre, are gone into Neutrall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, ſhall enjoy the fruits of this preſent Treaty, and may dwell where they ſhall pleaſe, yea returne to their old dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling places, for to live there with all ſecurity, obſerving the Lawes of the Countries, without that by reaſon of their dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling (which they ſhall keep in any place whatſoever) their goods be ſeized, or they deprived of the uſe of them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>58.</label> They ſhall not make any new Forts in the Netherlands, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on one ſide nor the other, nor dig any new paſſages or ditches, whereby they might ſhut in, or exclude the one or the other party.</p>
            <p>
               <label>59.</label> The Lords of the houſe of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> and alſo the Earle <hi>John Albert</hi> of <hi>Solms,</hi> Governours of <hi>Maeſtricht,</hi> ſhall not be ſued or moleſted in their perſons or goods, for any debts contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the late Lord Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> ſince the yeare 1567 untill his death, nor for the Intereſts fallen due during the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zure and ſequeſtring of the goods which were charged there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
            <p>
               <label>60.</label> In caſe any breach or contravention of this Treaty be made by any particular perſon, without command of the ſaid Lords the King or States, the dammage ſhall be repaired, at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place where the breach ſhall be done, in caſe they be there apprehended, or elſe at their dwelling places, without that they may be ſued any where elſe, in their perſons or goods, in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever manner it be, and they ſhall not be ſuffered to take up Armes, or break the Peace for it, but they ſhall have leave (in caſe of publike denyall of Juſtice) to help themſelves with let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Mart, or repriſall, as is uſuall.</p>
            <p>
               <label>61.</label> All diſinheritings and diſpoſitions done in hate of the warre are declared voyd, and held as not done; and by diſinheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances done in hate of the war, is meant, to comprehend thoſe which are happened by any cauſe, from whence the warre is riſen, and which depend thereon.</p>
            <p>
               <label>62.</label> The Subjects and Inhabitants of the lands of the ſaid Lords
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153480:12"/>the King or States, of whatſoever quality or condition they be, are declared capable to ſucceed one an other, as well by Teſtament as without a will, according to the cuſtome of the places, and in caſe any Succeſſions formerly befell any of them, they ſhall be received and preſerved therein.</p>
            <p>
               <label>63.</label> All priſoners of warre ſhall be diſcharged on the one ſide and the other, without paying any Ranſome, with a diſtinction or exception of ſuch priſoners as have ſerved out of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> and under other Standards and Colours then thoſe of the States.</p>
            <p>
               <label>64.</label> The payment of the arrerages of the contributions, which at the time of the Treaty ſhall remaine payable, in reſpect of the perſons and goods of the one and the other ſide, ſhall be regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and determined by thoſe who on both ſides have the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendance of the contributions.</p>
            <p>
               <label>65.</label> Whatſoever during the Treaty hath been propounded, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged on both ſides, verbally or in writing, ſhall not reach, nor may any wiſe be expounded to the benefit or detriment of any one, directly or indirectly, but aſwell the ſaid Lords, the King, and the States generall and particular, as alſo all Princes, Earles, Barons, Gentry, Citizens and other Inhabitants, of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Countries reſpectively, of whatſoever condition or quality they be, ſhall remaine in their rights, according to the contents of the Treaty, and the concluſion thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <label>66.</label> The Inhabitants and Subjects of the ſaid Lords, the King, and States reſpectively, ſhall really enjoy the effect of the 16.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the expired 12. yeares truce, and the effect of the 10.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Article of the Agreement, which followed thereupon the 8.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> 1610. and that for aſmuch as the ſaid effect was not performed by one or the other ſide during the time of the ſaid Truce.</p>
            <p>
               <label>67.</label> The bounds of <hi>Flanders</hi> and other parts, ſhall be regulated in ſuch manner as ſhall be found fitting, under the command of the one and the other ſide, the informations whereupon ſhall be expected and delivered, for to regulate the ſaid Limits in due time.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:153480:12"/>
            <p>
               <label>68.</label> On the behalfe and on the ſide of the ſaid Lord the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> ſhall be demoliſhed the Forts near and about <hi>Sluys:</hi> to wit, St. <hi>Jop.</hi> St. <hi>Denis, Sterre-ſchans,</hi> the Fort of <hi>Tereſſre,</hi> St. <hi>Frederix-Fort,</hi> the Fort St. <hi>Iſabelle,</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the Redouts <hi>Papemuts;</hi> and on the ſide and on the behalfe of the ſaid Lords States, ſhall be demoliſhed the Forts following; Namely, both the Forts in the land of <hi>Caſant</hi> called <hi>Orange,</hi> and <hi>Frederick,</hi> the two on the paſſage, and all thoſe which lye on the Eaſt ſide the river the <hi>Schelde,</hi> except <hi>Lillo,</hi> and the Fort on <hi>Kieldrecht</hi> called <hi>Spignola,</hi> for the demolition whereof on both ſides there ſhall be an agreement made between both parties, for to regulate it equally.</p>
            <p>
               <label>69.</label> All Regiſters, Charters, Deeds, Proofes, and Papers, as alſo buſineſſe of ſuits, concerning ſeverally any of the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, aſſociated Countries, Cities, or members of them, as alſo any particular Inhabitants of the ſame, remaining in the Courts, Chanceryes, Counſels, and Chambers of Policy, Juſtice, Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, Mannors, or Arches, either at <hi>Avenues, Mechelen,</hi> or other places under the obedience of the ſaid Lord the King ſhall in good ſaith, be delivered to thoſe, who from the ſide of the ſaid Provinces reſpectively, ſhall have commiſsion to demaund the ſame, and the like ſhall be done on the ſide of the ſaid Lords States, belonging to the uſe of the Provinces, Cities, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons under the obedience of the ſaid King.</p>
            <p>
               <label>70.</label> The water duty ſhall be left to the City of <hi>Sluys,</hi> as it belongs to it.</p>
            <p>
               <label>71.</label> The Dam made at Saint <hi>Denis</hi> for ſtopping of the river <hi>Sonte,</hi> ſhall be taken away and opened, provided a ſluce lye and be made there, for the keeping of which ſluce ſhall be equalized, as is here aforeſaid, in reſpect of the demoliſhing of the Forts.</p>
            <p>
               <label>72.</label> In the preſent Treaty of Peace ſhall be comprehended thoſe which before the inter-changing of the opprobative ratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or within three monthes after, ſhall be named on both ſides, within which time the ſaid Lord the King ſhall nominate whom
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153480:13"/>he thinks good; on the behalfe of the ſaid Lords States were nominated the Prince <hi>Landgrave</hi> of <hi>Haſſia, Caſſel,</hi> with his Towns, Cities and Countries, the Earle of <hi>Eaſt-Frieſland,</hi> the City of <hi>Embden,</hi> the County and Countrey of <hi>Eaſt Frieſland,</hi> the Hans-towns, and particularly <hi>Lubecke, Bremen, Hamburge,</hi> and the ſaid Lords States do reſerve to name within the ſaid time all ſuch others as they ſhall ſee good.</p>
            <p>
               <label>73.</label> Concerning the pretence of the Earle of <hi>Flodorp</hi> for reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be made to him of the houſe or mannor of <hi>Leuten,</hi> with the goods which may depend thereon, and all other goods and towns which may thereabouts belong to him, and are ſeized on the behalf of the ſaid Lord the King: the ſaid reſtitution is granted him, as alſo of the houſe, provided that between the concluſion of this preſent Treaty and the ratification thereof, a diſpoſition ſhall be made for the maintenance of a garriſon on the behalfe of the ſaid Lord the King, and for the demoliſhing of the new for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications made ſince the poſſeſſing of the ſaid houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>74.</label> Concerning what was treated and agreed on between the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Ambaſſadours and Plenipotentiaries of the ſaid Lord the King, and States, on the eighth of <hi>December</hi> 1646. concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Rutger Huygens,</hi> for and in the name of his wife Miſtreſſe <hi>Anna Margareta van Stralen,</hi> it ſhall have ſuch force and effect, and ſhall be performed and executed, in all points, as if the ſame were inſerted word for word in this preſent Treaty.</p>
            <p>
               <label>75.</label> And to the end this preſent Treaty may the better be kept, the ſaid Lord the King and States do ſeverally promiſe to aſſiſt, and each one in his place to uſe their might and means, to make the paſſages free, and to make the ſea and rivers navigable, and ſure againſt the incurſions of <hi>Pyrats,</hi> ſea rovers, vagabonds, and theeves, and if they can apprehend them, to puniſh them with rigour.</p>
            <p>
               <label>76.</label> They further promiſe, to do nothing againſt or in prejudice of this preſent Treaty, nor ſuffer to be done directly or indirectly, and in caſe it be done, to cauſe reparation to be made without any trouble or delay, And for the performance of all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153480:13"/>they bind themſelves ſeverally (yea, the Lord the King his own ſelfe, and his ſucceſſours) and for the ſtability of the ſame obligation, they renounce all lawes, cuſtomes, and all other things to the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <label>77.</label> This preſent Treaty ſhall be ratified and approved by the ſaid Lords, the King and States, and the Letters of ratification on both ſides ſhall be delivered up from one to the other in good and due forme, within the time of two monthes, and in caſe the ſame ratification can come ſooner, all acts of hoſtility between both partyes ſhall ceaſe from that time, without tarrying the expiration of the tearme: Provided that after the concluding and ſubſcribing of this preſent Treaty, the hoſtility ſhall not ceaſe before and untill the ratification of the ſaid Lord the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> ſhall be produced in due ſubſtance and forme. and inter changed for that of the ſaid Lords the States of the United Provinces.</p>
            <p>
               <label>78.</label> So that in the mean time things on both ſides ſhall remain in ſuch ſtate and condition as they ſhall be found at the time of the concluding of this preſent Treaty, and untill that the ſaid reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procall ratification ſhall be inter-changed and delivered.</p>
            <p>
               <label>79.</label> The ſaid Treaty ſhall every where and where it is fitting be publiſhed, preſently after that the ſaid ratifications on both ſides ſhall be inter-changed and delivered up, and then all Acts of Hoſtility ſhall ceaſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:153480:14"/>
            <head>A COPY Of the full power of his Royall Majeſtie of <hi>Spaine</hi> which was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the Ambaſſadors of the High and Mightie Lords the States Generall of the Vnited <hi>Netherlands,</hi> being at preſent aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled at <hi>Munſter;</hi> wherein his royall Majeſtie declareth the Vnited <hi>Netherlands</hi> to be free and franke, without that he hath any pretence on them in any manner; as followeth.</head>
            <p>DON PHILIP by the grace of God King of <hi>Caſtile, Leon, Arragon,</hi> the two <hi>Sicilies, Jeruſalem, Portugall, Navarr, Granada, Toledo, Valentia, Gullicia, Majorca, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norca, Sivill, Sardinia, Cordua, Corſica, Murcia, Jaen,</hi> the <hi>Algarves, Algerica, Gibraltar,</hi> the <hi>Canary Ilands,</hi> the Eaſt and Weſt <hi>Indies,</hi> the Ilands and firme land of the <hi>Ocean Sea;</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundie, Brabant, Millaine,</hi> Earle of <hi>Absburg, Flanders, Tiroll</hi> and <hi>Barcelona,</hi> Lord of <hi>Biſcaye</hi> and <hi>Mechelen,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Whereas I do ſo far and ſo much deſire to advance the reſt and tranquilitie of the Subjects and Inhabitants of the Provinces of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> that they may ceaſe from ſuch a long cruell war, for the better attainiug of a generall Peace in Europe, for the good of Chriſtendome; And having by common and mutuall conſent choſen and appointed the City of <hi>Munſter</hi> in <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalia,</hi> for the Aſſembly and Treaty of the ſaid Peace, I have found it convenient to nominate perſons, who may in my name aſſiſt at the ſaid Aſſembly with all authoritie and full power, and eſpecially with the States of the free Provinces of the United <hi>Netherlands,</hi> or their Ambaſſadors, and Plenipotentiaries, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly authorized and deputed, and taking into conſideration the ſufficient integritie, circumſpection, experience, judgement and zeale to my Service, and the good of the reſt of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in generall, which do concur in the Perſons of <hi>Don Gaſpar de Braccamonte</hi> and <hi>Guſman</hi> Earle of <hi>Peneranda,</hi> Gentlemen of of my Counſell Chamber, and of the Chamber of Juſtice, as alſo of my Extraordinary Ambaſſador in <hi>Germanie,</hi> Fryer <hi>Ioſeph Ergaigne</hi> Arch Biſhop of <hi>Cambray,</hi> and <hi>Anthony Brun</hi> of my
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153480:14"/>High Counſell in <hi>Flanders;</hi> and for the ſatisfaction they have alwayes given me in ſeverall and great negotiations which were laid upon them, and by them ſeverally treated, therefore fully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving, that they all together, and each one in particular in the abſence or inconvenience of one or the other, will have regard to the beſt welfare of Chriſtendome, and my particular intereſts, I have nominated them for my Ambaſſadors and Plenipotentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and by vertue of theſe preſents, I give them jointly, and to each one in particular in the abſence or inconvenience of any of them, full and abſolute power to make an overture to the States of the ſaid free Provinces of the United <hi>Netherlands,</hi> or to their Ambaſſadors, and Plenipotentiaries, who ſhall be thereunto eſpecially authoriſed and conſtituted: As alſo to heare what ſhall be propounded to the pacifying of the ſaid long and cruell war, moved in the Provinces of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and ſuch which have growne from thence againſt the ſaid States Generall in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lands and ſeas, lying far off, And in ſequell thereof to enter into an accomodation with the ſaid States general of the ſaid free United Provinces, or with their ſaid Ambaſſadours and Plenipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiaries to confer, propound, agree, capitulate, and conclude, a good, firme, and inviolable Treaty of reſt, either of Peace or of a Truce, promiſing for my Self and my Succeſſors for ever, to hold firme and valid, preciſely and punctually, without any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault, whatſoever by my ſaid Ambaſſadours and Plenipotentiaries joyntly, or by each in particular in the abſence or inconvenience of any of them, ſhall be agreed and capitulated in the ſaid Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with the ſaid States Generall, or their ſaid Ambaſſadors and Plenipotentiaries of the ſaid United free Provinces: And alſo to approve and ratifie it my ſelfe, within the time which ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocally appointed, with corroboration of an oath and all ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities in ſuch caſe needfull and uſuall; In witneſſe whereof I have commanded to diſpateh theſe preſents, Subſcribed with my hand, and counter-ſigned with the Subſcription of my Secretarie of State;</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> 
                  <date>the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>June</hi> 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>I the King. P. Coloma.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="procuration">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:153480:15"/>
            <head>The Contents of the Procuration of the Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotentiaries of the Lords the States Generall.</head>
            <p>THe States generall of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces, to all thoſe who ſhall ſee theſe Preſents, or heare them read, greeting, Do make known, That whereas we have heretofore upon all occaſions ſhewed our ſelves very ready, with an upright will and intention, that the long-during, deſtructive, and bloudy Warre in the Low-countrey Provinces, moved many yeares ſince, and continuing till this preſent, might have been laid aſide, for the common good of the ſaid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, and comfort of the good Inhabitants of the ſame; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by have alſo followed and grown the Warres in other places, and ſeas, lying a far off, which have riſen againſt our Adverſary, out of the ſaid Low-countrey Warre; And having by common conſent choſen the City of <hi>Munſter</hi> in <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> for the aſſembling and treating of a generall Peace in <hi>Chriſtendome;</hi> We have thought good to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate perſons who with all authority and full power ſhould aſſiſt at the ſaid Aſſembly &amp; Treaty, for to helpe to put an end to the ſaid te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, deſtructive, and bloudy Warre moved in the Low-countreys sa aforeſaid: Therefore fully truſting on the wiſdome diſcretion, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection, fidelity, and zeale to the ſervice of the ſaid <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces, of the Lords <hi>Bartholt van Gendt,</hi> Lord of <hi>Loeven, Meynerſwyck, &amp;c: Amptman</hi> and <hi>Dyckgrave</hi> of <hi>Bommel, Tielre,</hi> and <hi>Bommelerweerde,</hi> deputed for the Aſſembly of the Lords States generall out of the Province of <hi>Gelderland;</hi> The Lord <hi>John van Matheneſſe,</hi> Lord of <hi>Mateneſſe, Ryver Opmeer, Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teveen,</hi> deputed for the Aſſembly of the Lords the States generall by the Order of the Knighthood and Gentry of <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friezeland;</hi> The Lord <hi>Adrian Pauw</hi> Knight, Lord of <hi>Hamſted, Hogerſmilde, &amp;c.</hi> Chiefe preſiding Chancellour and Treaſurer of the County of <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friezeland,</hi> and on the behalfe of the ſame Province, deputed for the Aſſembly of the Lords the States generall; The Lord <hi>John de Knuyt,</hi> Knight, Lord of the old and new <hi>Doſmer,</hi> chiefe and repreſenting the Gentry of the States, and the Counſell of the County of <hi>Sealand,</hi> and of the Admiralty there, Chiefe Councellour of his Highneſſe the Lord Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> ordinary Deputy at the Aſſembly of the Lords the States geuerall;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153480:15"/>The Lord <hi>Godart van Reede,</hi> Lord of <hi>Nederhorſt, Uredeſant, Short-hoofe, Orermeer, Horſt, Waeſt, &amp;c:</hi> Preſident of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Gentry and Knights of the Laud of <hi>Vytrecht,</hi> and in their names appearing at the Aſſembly of the Lords States generall; The Lord <hi>Francis van Donia</hi> Lord of <hi>Humena,</hi> and <hi>Hialſum,</hi> &amp;c. deputed for the Aſſembly of the Lords the States generall on the behalfe of the Province of <hi>Friezland;</hi> The Lord <hi>William Ripperda,</hi> Lord of <hi>Hengeloo, Bolburgen, Cavulo,</hi> and <hi>Ruſſenburge, &amp;c.</hi> deputed for the Aſſembly of the States generall by the Knighthood and Gentry of the Province of <hi>Over Yſel;</hi> The Lord <hi>Adrian Clant at Stedum,</hi> Lord of <hi>Mutterſum, &amp;c.</hi> ordinary Deputy in the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of the Lords States generall on the behalfe of the Province of the City of <hi>Groningen,</hi> and lands adjacent; the reſpective Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in our Aſſembly, and extraordinary Ambaſſadours in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> giving unto them joyntly, or at leaſt to the greateſt part of them (in the abſence or inconvenience of the other) full power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, generall and ſpeciall Command, for in our names, and on our behalfe in the quality of Plenipotentiaries of this ſtate, in the ſaid city of <hi>Munſter,</hi> to heare and underſtand from the Lords Plenipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiaries of the mighty and moſt excellent Prince <hi>Don Phillip</hi> the fourth King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the overture of what the ſame Lords Plenipotentiaries of the ſaid King ſhall produce, for the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the ſaid tedious, deſtructive, and bloudy Warre, moved in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and which hath cauſed warre againſt our adverſaries, in places and ſeas lying a far off, and in order hereunto to enter into a Treaty and Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation with the ſaid Lords Plenipotentiaries of the ſaid King, and to conclude a good, firme, juſt, and infrangible Treaty of Peace, as the Lords Plenipotentiaries of this State ſhall judge fit, for the moſt ſervice and aſſurance of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces, the good Inhabitants thereof, and their Aſſociates, and the intereſted in the ſaid ſeverall tedious warres; And we have promiſed and do promiſe by theſe Preſents in good faith, and under obligation of our ſelves, and our ſucceſſours, in generall and in particular, alwayes to hold good, firme, and of value, what by our ſaid Plenipotentiaries concerning this ſhall be agreed and concluded, and to ratifie the ſame, and infrangibly to keep it, and cauſe it to be kept, without ever to do, or ſuffer to be done againſt it in any maner directly or indirectly: <hi>In witneſſe</hi> hereof we have cauſed theſe Preſents to be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153480:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>paraphed, cauſed it to be ſealed with our great Seale, and to be ſubſcribed by our Secretary.</p>
            <p>In our Aſſembly in the <hi>Hage,</hi> the twentieth of <hi>March 1646.</hi> Parafied: <hi>Johan van Reede:</hi> on the fold was written, by Order of the ſaid high Lords States generall and ſubſcribed <hi>Corn: Muſch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having the great Seale of the Lords States generall in red wax, under appending, at a double ribbon of gold and red ſilke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In witneſſe</hi> of all that which is afore ſaid, we the Extraordinary Ambaſſadours and Plenipotentiaries of the ſaid Lords, the King of <hi>Spaine, &amp;c.</hi> and of the States generall of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited <hi>Netherlands,</hi> by virtue of our ſeverall Procurations or Letters of Atturney, have ſubſcribed this preſent Treaty, and corroborated it with the Seales of our Armes.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Done in</hi> Munſter <hi>in</hi> Weſtphalia <date>
                     <hi>the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of</hi> January, <hi>1648.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <head>was Subſcribed and Sealed:</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Earl of</hi> Peneranda.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A. Brun.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bartholt van Gent.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn van Matheneſſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Adrian Pauw.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>I. de Knuyt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>F. van Donia.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>VVilliam Ripperda.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Adrian Clandt.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153480:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
